Guide to the W. E. Hook Photographs of Colorado, New Mexico, and Texas
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
W. E. Hook photographs of Colorado, New Mexico, and Texas.
1885-1908
WA Photos 511
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.5
(2 boxes)
Photographs collected by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library that document the photography of W. E. Hook, 1885-1908. The collection chiefly includes photographs of sites in Colorado, as well as some images of New Mexico and Texas. Photographs in the collection document the different presentation methods used by Hook to market his images, including cabinet photographs, as well as the variant titles he used in negatives and on photographic mounts.
Hook, W. E. (William Edward), 1833-1908
General note
Title devised by cataloger.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase. For more information see the finding aid.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
W. E. Hook (1833-1908)
William Edward Hook (1833-1908) was born in Litchfield, England. His family immigrated briefly to the United States in 1834, but returned to England by 1851. In 1857, he married Eleanor Jane Dore (circa 1833-1914) and they had six children.
In 1867, Hook returned to the United States without his family. Two years later he established a photography studio in Chippewa Falls, Wisconsin. In February 1875, two of his sons joined him in the United States: Theodore Hook (circa 1859-circa 1875) and William Edward Hook, Jr. (circa 1864-1907).
In 1877, Hook closed his photography studio in Wisconsin, and he and his surviving son, William, worked as traveling photographers from a home base in Missoula, Montana. Over the next four years, they travelled and captured images throughout Montana and Wyoming, including Yellowstone National Park, Alberta, Northwest Territory, and the Canadian Northwest Rockies. By 1881, Hook established a photography studio in Marquette, Michigan, from which he marketed his images of the American West.
In April 1885, Hook established a photography studio in Manitou Springs, Colorado. In September 1885, he filed a homestead claim on the nearby Ruxton Creek near Pikes Peak, which he named "Artist's Glen." Over the years, Hook specialized in marketing landscape views of Colorado to tourists.
In 1887, Hook traveled to England. He returned to Colorado with his wife and their daughters, Eleanor "Nellie" Hook (born circa 1858) and Alice M. Hook (born circa 1864, later Mrs. Edward M. De La Vergne); their son, William also rejoined the family. Over the years, the Hook family filed additional homestead claims around Ruxton Creek. They also operated a boarding house for tourists until 1890, when the construction and operations associated with the Manitou and Pike's Peak Railway – a steep grade railway from Manitou Springs to the summit of Pikes Peak – prompted the family to relocate to Colorado Springs. Hook then operated a photography studio in Colorado Springs until his death from heart failure.
Scope and Contents
Photographs collected by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library that document the photography of W. E. Hook, 1885-1908. The collection chiefly includes photographs of sites in Colorado, as well as some images of New Mexico and Texas. Photographs in the collection document the different presentation methods used by Hook to market his images, including cabinet photographs, as well as the variant titles he used in negatives and on photographic mounts.
Images of sites in Colorado include Cascade Canyon, Cheyenne Mountain, Colorado Springs, Garden of the Gods, Leadville, Manitou Springs, Mount of the Holy Cross, North Cheyenne Canyon, Pikes Peak, Royal Gorge, South Cheyenne Canyon, Ute Pass, and Williams Canyon. An exterior group portrait of Ute Indians in Colorado includes Chief Sapiah, also known as Buckskin Charlie. Images of New Mexico consist of an overview of Santa Fe and an exterior group portrait of Tewa Indians at the Tesuque Pueblo. The collection also includes a view of the Franklin School in El Paso, Texas.
Arrangement
Organized into one series: I. Photographs, 1885-1908.
Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Tewa Indians -- Pictorial works; Ute Indians -- Pictorial works; Cascade Canyon (El Paso County, Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Cheyenne Mountain (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Colorado -- Pictorial works; Colorado Springs (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; El Paso (Tex.) -- Pictorial works; Garden of the Gods (Colorado Springs, Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Holy Cross, Mount of the (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Leadville (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Manitou Springs (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; New Mexico -- Pictorial works; North Cheyenne Canyon (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Pikes Peak (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Royal Gorge (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Santa Fe (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; South Cheyenne Canyon (Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Tesuque Pueblo (N.M.) -- Pictorial works; Texas -- Pictorial works; Ute Pass (Teller County, Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Williams Canyon (El Paso County, Colo.) -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Buckskin Charlie, Ute chief -- Pictorial works; Hook, W. E. (William Edward), 1833-1908; Franklin School (El Paso, Tex.) -- Pictorial works
- Photographs, 1885-1908; Series I; 42
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Colorado, New Mexico, and Texas
  Scope and Contents
  Photographs that chiefly document sites in Colorado, as well as New Mexico and Texas
  - Colorado
    - Cascade Canyon
      - View of Peek-A-Boo Falls in Cascade Canyon near Cascade, Colorado, with a woman posed sitting on a boulder, circa 1890-1908; 18.5 x 11.2 cm on mount 20.2 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Immediate Source of Acquisition
        Source unknown
        Printed in negative: "Peek-a-Boo Falls, Cascade Colo., 454"
        Blindstamp on recto: "The W. E. Hook Wholesale View Co., Colorado Springs, Colo."
    - Cheyenne Mountain
      - View of the grave site of Helen (Fiske) Hunt Jackson on Cheyenne Mountain, Colorado., circa 1890-1908; 11.1 x 18.4 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Image shows a large pile of stones, a cairn, which marks the grave in a forest.
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 202 Grave Mrs. Jackson. (H. H.) Cheyenne Mountain"
        Inscription on verso: "F. F."
        Purchased from Thomas C. Klopp on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 2013
    - Colorado Springs
      - View of the Broadmoor Casino in Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1891-1897; 10.7 x 18.4 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
        View of the casino, a two-story frame building with a colonnaded, pedimented entry, and balustrades, as well as a wrap-around porch and balcony. Its lawn has a pavilion and planted flower letters that form "Broadmoor"
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo"
        Blindstamp on recto: "The W. E. Hook Wholesale View Co., Colorado Springs, Col."
    - Garden of the Gods
      - View of Balanced Rock, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 18.9 x 11.3 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Image shows a large sandstone boulder balanced on a rock ledge
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 115 Balanced Rock, Garden of the Gods"
        Ink stamp on verso: "509 N. Tejon St., Colorado Springs, Colorado., W. E. Hook, view and portrait photographer, Colorado Wholesale View House"
      - View of Balanced Rock, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, with a man posed standing, circa 1890-1908; 18.5 x 11.2 cm on mount 20.7 X 12.6 cm (Box 1, Folder 5)
        The original negative broken in the lower left quarter of the photograph
        Printed in negative: "Balanced Rock, Garden of the Gods"
        Ink stamp on verso: "From the W. E. Hook View Company, 509 North Tejon St., Colorado Springs, Colorado"
      - View of Balanced Rock, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 18.8 x 11.1 cm on mount 20.7 X 12.6 cm (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Inscription in negative: "Balanced Rock, Garden of the Gods"
      - View of Cathedral Spires, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado., circa 1885-1908; 18.5 x 10.9 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Printed in negative: "85 Cathedral Spires"
      - View of Gate Rock, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 11.1 x 18.4 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Image shows dirt roads and snow on Pikes Peak in the distance.
        Printed in negative: "108 Gateway, Garden of the Gods, Hook Photo"
      - View of Gate Rock, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, with snow-covered Pikes Peak in the distance, circa 1890-1908; 11.1 x 18.4 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, Gateway, Garden of the Gods, 534
        Ink stamp on verso: "Adolph Segnitz, Milwaukee"
        Inscription on verso: "California Excursion Feby-Mch 1894"
      - View of Ruins of Montezuma's Temple, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 18.4 x 11.4 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, Ruins of Montezuma's Temple, Garden of the Gods, 561"
        Pencil inscriptions on recto and verso: "Seitz"
      - View of Ruins of Montezuma's Temple, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 11.1 x 18.3 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Printed in negative: "Ruins of Montezuma's Temple, Garden of the Gods, 538, Hook Photo"
      - View of Seal and Bear, rock formations at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 11.1 x 18.3 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 138 Seal and Bear, Garden of the Gods"
      - View of Seal and Bear, rock formations at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 11.6 x 19.2 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Inscription on recto: "Seal & Bear, Garden of the Gods"
      - View of Tower of Babel, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 18.9 x 11.3 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 128, Tower of Babel, Garden of the Gods"
      - View of Tower of Babel, a rock formation at Garden of the Gods near Colorado Springs, Colorado, with a horse and carriage at its foot, circa 1890-1908; 19.5 x 11.4 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Inscription in negative: "Tower of Babel, Garden of the Gods"
    - Leadville
      - View of Leadville, Colorado, from Carbonate Hill, circa 1890-1908; 10.9 x 18.7 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 1606, Leadville, from Carbonate Hill"
      - View of Leadville, Colorado, from Carbonate Hill, circa 1890-1908; 11.0 x 18.7 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 1618, Leadville, from Carbonate Hill"
      - View of the Wolftone Mine, near Leadville, Lake County, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 11.0 x 18.3 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Printed in negative: "Wolftone Mine, Leadville"
      - View of mines at Leadville, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 10.8 x 18.3 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Printed in negative: "Mines of Leadville"
    - Manitou Springs
      - View of Manitou Springs, Colorado, looking southwest, which shows houses and commercial buildings including the "Hiawatha Concert Gardens," as well as the Denver and Rio Grande railroad, circa 1890-1900; 11.2 x 18.5 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Printed in negative: "582, Manitou Springs, Hook Photo"
        Printed on recto: "The W. E. Hook Wholesale View Co., Colorado Springs, Colo."
      - View of Manitou Springs, Colorado, looking southwest, which shows houses and commercial buildings including the "Hiawatha Concert Gardens," as well as the Denver and Rio Grande railroad, circa 1892-1908; 11.2 x 18.4 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.1 cm (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Inscription on recto: "Manitou"
        Printed on verso: "The W. E. Hook View Company, 509 North Tejon Street, Colorado Springs, Colorado. The most marvellous cloud scenes in water colors, ever photographed: 25 cts each. Sunset from the Mesa. Pike's Peak above the clouds. Sunset from Gateway, Garden of the Gods. Sunrise from summit of Pike's Peak"
    - Mount of the Holy Cross
      - Copy photograph of a painting, Mountain of the Holy Cross (1875), by Thomas Moran, which depicts Mount of the Holy Cross in Eagle County, Colorado, with an imagined waterfall in the foreground, circa 1890-1908; 18.4 x 11.1 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Printed in negative: "164 Mountain of the Holy Cross"
        Ink stamp on verso: "The W. E. Hook View Company, 509 North Tejon St., Colorado Springs, Colorado, W. E. Hook, view and portrait photographer, Colorado Wholesale View House"
    - North Cheyenne Canyon
      - View of the Silver Cascades waterfall on North Cheyenne Creek in North Cheyenne Canyon, El Paso County, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 18.5 x 11.3 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 572, Silver Cascades, North Cheyenne Canon"
      - View of the Silver Cascades waterfall on North Cheyenne Creek in North Cheyenne Canyon, El Paso County, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 18.3 x 11.1 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Printed in negative: "1195, Silver Cascades, Cheyenne Canon, Hook Photo"
        Ink stamp on verso: "The W. E. Hook View Company, 509 North Tejon Street, Colorado Springs, Colorado"
    - Pikes Peak
      - View of a sunrise above stratocumulus clouds from the summit of Pikes Peak in El Paso County, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 11.1 x 18.5 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Printed in negative: "Sunrise, from Summit Pike's Peak, 293, Hook Photo"
      - View looking east-southeast from summit of Pikes Peak in El Paso County, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 11.2 x 19.0 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 26)
        Image shows granite gravel in the foreground with mountains in the distance
        Printed in negative: "View from Summit Pike's Peak, 296, Hook Photo"
      - View of Pikes Peak in Colorado between two rock formations, circa 1885-1889; 11.3 x 18.4 cm on mount 14.9 x 24 cm (Box 1, Folder 27)
        Printed on recto: "Pike's Peak, Rock Mountains. -Series 1- Negatives made on Anthony's Climax Negative Films," and "Negatives by W. E. Hook, Manitou Springs, Colo. Printed on N.P.A. Extra Brilliant Pensé Albumen Paper"
      - View of Pikes Peak in Colorado with rocks and conifir trees in the foreground, circa 1885-1889; 11.2 x 18.4 cm on mount 14.9 x 23.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Printed on recto: "Pike's Peak, Rock Mountains. -Series 2- Negatives made on Anthony's Climax Negative Films," and "Negatives by W. E. Hook, Manitou Springs, Colo. Printed on N.P.A. Extra Brilliant Pensé Albumen Paper"
    - Royal Gorge
      - View of the Hanging Bridge of the Denver and Rio Grande Railroad over the Arkansas River in the Royal Gorge located in Fremont County, Colorado., circa 1890-1908; 18.3 x 11.1 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Printed in negative: "1586, Hanging Bridge, Royal Gorge, Hook Photo"
        Ink stamp on verso: "Chas. A. Grant, Views, Native Jewelry and Specimens, Manitou Springs, Colo."
    - South Cheyenne Canyon
      - View of the "The Narrows" section of South Cheyenne Canyon southwest of the Broadmoor, near Colorado Springs, Colorado with four men standing on a road, circa 1890-1908; 18.8 x 11.2 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 30)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 200, Narrows, Cheyenne Can"
      - View of the "The Narrows" section of South Cheyenne Canyon southwest of the Broadmoor, near Colorado Springs, Colorado, with a woman sitting near the road, circa 1890-1894; 18.4 x 11.2 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 201, Narrows, Cheyenne Canon"
    - Ute Pass
      - View of Bath of Venus waterfall in Ute Pass, northwest of Manitou Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908; 18.4 x 11.1 cm on mount 20.3 x 12.7 cm (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 447, Narrows, Bath of Venus, Ute Pass"
        Printed on verso for "The W. E. Hook View, Stationery and Book Company, 27 South Tejon Street, Colorado Springs, Colorado," as well as descriptions of images offered for sale by Hook
        Ink inscription on verso: "M. B. Roberts, Colo. Springs"
      - View of Rainbow Falls on Twin Creek near Ute Pass in Teller County, Colorado, which also shows large rock boulders, circa 1890-1908; 19.1 x 11.6 cm on mount 20.7 X 12.6 cm (Box 1, Folder 33)
        Printed in negative: "1879, Rainbow Falls"
        Printed advertisement on verso: "From the W. E. Hook View, Stationery and Book Company, 509 North Tejon Street, Colorado Springs, Colorado, ..."
    - Williams Canyon
      - View of a man standing on a dirt road winding through a narrow portion of Williams Canyon, north of Manitou Springs, Colorado, circa 1890-1908 (Box 1, Folder 34)
        Printed in negative: "Narrows Wms Canon"
        Printed on recto: "W. E. Hook, photographer and publisher of American scenery from ocean to ocean"
        Printed advertisement on verso: "'The Pines,' Monument Park,... Edgerton, Colo."
      - View of Williams Canyon and cliffs with Manitou Springs, Colorado, and mountains in the distance, circa 1885-1908; 11.2 x 18.4 cm on mount 24.8 X 35.8 cm (Box 2, Folder 35)
        Printed in negative: "Hook Photo, 212, A Glimpse of Manitou from Williams Canon"
    - Unidentified Locations
      - Exterior group portrait of Ute Indian men, women, children, and a baby, as well as European American men., circa 1885-1890 (Box 1, Folder 36)
        The portrait includes Chief Sapiah (circa 1840-1936), also known as Charles Buck or Buckskin Charlie, posed standing with fur wrapped braids, a hairpipe breastplate, concho belt and a feather in his hair. The Ute Indian men wear hair pipe breastplates, beaded sashes, printed fabric, conchos, leggings, moccasins and feather headdresses, roaches, and or feathers. The women wear beaded or quilled buckskin dresses. Children play with toys on woven blankets by a baby in a cradleboard decorated with beadwork and quillwork.
        Printed in negative: "Copyright, Hook Photo, 1681, Chief Buckskin Charlie and Band of Ute Indians"
        Inscription on verso: "Hook (Colorado), Chief Buckskin Charlie and his band of Ute Indians. Note Indian with glasses"
      - Exterior portrait of a donkey, named "Satan," with a saddle and reins, circa 1890-1894; 11.2 x 18.9 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.2 cm (Box 1, Folder 37)
        Printed in negative: "They call me 'Satan,' 559, Hook Photo"
        Inscription on verso recounting a mountain trip by an unidentified female tourist mounted on the donkey through South Cheyenne Canyon and over Cheyenne Mountain on August 2, 1894
      - Exterior portrait of a donkey with an empty pack saddle, circa 1890-1908; 11.2 x 19.0 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.2 cm (Box 1, Folder 38)
        Printed in negative: "The Mountain Freighter, Hook Photo, 803"
      - View of a lake and forest, circa 1890-1908; 12.1 x 17.8 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - New Mexico
    - Santa Fe
      - View of Santa Fe, New Mexico, circa 1890-1908; 11.2 x 18.5 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.2 cm (Box 1, Folder 40)
        Printed in negative: "Santa Fe, New Mex., 823, Hook Photo"
        Printed description on verso with the title, "The Pueblo Indians and Indian Pueblos," as well as advertising for the Santa Fé Route of the Atchison, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway and the "The W. E. Hook Wholesale View Company, Colorado Springs, Colorado"
    - Tesuque Pueblo
      - Exterior group portrait of Tewa Indians at the Tesuque Pueblo, New Mexico, circa 1890-1908; 11.4 x 18.5 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 41)
        Printed in negative: "Pueblo Indians. Tesuqua, N.M., 1106"
        Inscription on verso: "Pueblo Indians. Tesudua, N.M."
  - Texas
    - El Paso
      - View of the Franklin School at Leon Street and West Overland Avenue, El Paso, Texas, with students in front, circa 1890-1908; 10.9 x 18.3 cm on mount 12.7 x 20.3 cm (Box 1, Folder 42)
        Hand colored photographic print
        Printed in negative: "El Paso, Texas, 1311"
        Inkstamp on verso: "From Mexican and Indian Curio Co., El Paso, Texas"